Finding aid for the Nick Smirnoff papers LSC.2247
UCLA Library Special Collections
Nick Smirnoff papers
1970-2009
UCLA Library Special Collections
Smirnoff, Nick
LSC.2247
16.4 Linear Feet (30 boxes, 3 record cartons, 1 shoe box, 3 flat boxes)
Nick Smirnoff was a production manager, assistant director, producer and photographer who has worked primarily between the 1970's-2000's in Los Angeles. His work includes numerous projects in the television industry, in addition to motion pictures and commercials. His most notable projects include Felicity, The Toolbox Murders, and Miami Vice. The collection is comprised of production and industry materials such as scripts, production reports, crew and cast contact lists, and publications containing industry guidelines and procedures.
Conditions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: This collection contains processed digital materials. All requests to access digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift, 2016. Donated by Nick and Catherine Smirnoff.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9980587053606533
Biography/History
Nick R. Smirnoff was a production manager, producer and assistant director who has worked primarily in the television industry. Smirnoff was born in Santa Cruz, California in 1944 and was raised in the San Fernando Valley. He entered the film industry working as a gofer by way of his brother, David Smirnoff, who was a cameraman for FilmFair productions. Smirnoff earned an AA in theater arts and film from Valley College before serving three tours in Vietnam as a photographer in the Marines. Upon his return, Smirnoff went on to be a union craftsperson for FilmFair, working his way up to assistant director. From 1982-2009 Smirnoff worked as a Production Manager on projects such as T.J. Hooker, Coach, and Reasonable Doubts. Smirnoff has also worked as an assistant director on projects such as Miami Vice, Vega$, and ChiPS. From 1994-2000 Smirnoff was a co-producer on the television shows Felicity, and Silk Stalkings. Smirnoff has also worked as a still photographer, and exhibits his personal photographic work. He currently has a website, www.glasseyephotos.net, in which he displays his fine art, photojournalism and commercial work. Smirnoff retired in 2009 and currently lives with his wife Catherine in Tehachapi, California. His son, Chris Smirnoff, is an Emmy-award winning producer for the television show Modern Family.
Scope and Content
Containing materials between the 1970's and 2000's, this collection is comprised of production and industry materials, as well as ephemera from Nick Smirnoff's career as a production manager, assistant director, producer, location manager, and still photographer. The collection contains material that documents the tasks involved within these roles, giving an insight into the behind the scenes work of the film industry. Within the collection are production files from television and motion picture works that document many phases of production such as scheduling, equipment budgets, reports, location scouting, vendor correspondence, promotion, and crew management. This collection also contains a breadth of publications by Los Angeles based film industry associations and unions such as the Directors Guild of America, The Screen Actors Guild, The International Cinematographers Guild, The Alliance of Motion Picture and Television Producers, and various local unions. These publications document a span of industry guidelines and procedures such as safety protocols, labor practices, union rules, insurance, and U.S. and international visas.
Organization and Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Projects, 1975-2009
Series 2: Industry Material, 1970-2009
Series 3: Industry Ephemera, 1980-2009
Related Material
Related materials providing documentation of production manager and assistant director duties may be found in the following collections in this repository:
Bob Jeffords Papers (Collection 197)
Ralph John Slosser Papers (Collection 164)
Television producers and directors -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Motion picture producers and directors -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Smirnoff, Nick -- Archives
- Series 1: Projects, 1975-2000's
  Scope and Content
  This series contains material relating to projects Smirnoff worked on as a production manager, producer, assistant director, location manager and still photographer from the 1970's-2000's. The projects are mostly comprised of television series, but also include motion pictures, television movies, and television commercials. Materials include scripts, budgets, cast and crew lists, newspaper clippings, magazines, daily production reports, call sheets, and promotional material. Notable projects include Felicity, Miami Vice, ChiPS, Vega$, and Silk Stalkings. Projects were completed with many prominent studios such as Disney, Castlerock Entertainment, Warner Brothers, CBS, Brillstein-Grey, Columbia Pictures, Lorimar Productions, and Paramount Pictures. This series also contains a Macintosh PowerBook G3 that Smirnoff used for production scheduling, as well as floppy disks containing software and Smirnoff's Helix Express database. This series contains explicit adult material.
  Organization and Arrangement
  This series has been organized alphabetically by project.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  COLLECTION CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk in advance of your visit.
  - Adventures in Babysitting, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The American Girls, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Amerika, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 1-3, Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Among the Hills, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Arsenio Hall Project, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bear Lake Run, July 19, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Body and Soul, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Boogie Boy, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Budgets, 1993-2001 (Box 24, Folder 5-6)
  - The Cat From Outer Space, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Child Stealer, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - CHiPS, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clear and Present Danger, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Coach, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Columbo, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 1, Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Commercials, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Criminal Mastermind, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 5, Box 4, Folder 2-4)
  - A Cross Too Many, circa 1980's (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Dear John, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Death of a Centerfold: The Dorothy Stratten Story, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
    Box 3, Folder 7 contains an adult periodical.
  - Delta County, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Enemy Within, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 7-8, Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Fantasy Island, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Felicity, 1998-2000 (Box 7, Folder 1-2, Box 6, Folder 1-4, Box 5, Folder 3-7)
  - Flying Lessons, April 4, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - For Love and Money, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Francis Gary Powers Story, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Future Girls, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Gemini, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Genie (You Wish), 1997 (Box 8, Folder 1-3, Box 7, Folder 5-6)
  - The Girl Who Struck Out Babe Ruth, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Glitter, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Go the Distance, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Goldie and the Boxer, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - The Greatest American Hero, 1981-1982 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - The Healer, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    This folder contains adult illustrations.
  - Heart of a Champion: The Ray Mancini Story, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Hiller and Diller, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Hoax, 1985-1986 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Hollywood Palms, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Home Again (Back to You and Me), 2004 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Hunter, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 5, Box 10, Folder 3)
  - I Accuse (The Phantom), 1990 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Ice Capades with Peter Scolari, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - The Iceman, 1977-1978 (Box 23, Folder 8)
    Material in this folder pertains to the lawsuit filed by Smirnoff with Cinevest International over unpaid wages and severance pay for his work on The Iceman.
  - Infidelity, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Institute for Revenge, 1978-1979 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Is Anybody There?, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - The Jeff Foxworthy Show, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Jonas, 2007 (Box 11, Folder 1-2, Box 10, Folder 8, Box 9, Folder 9-11)
  - Just Shoot Me, 2002 (Box 11, Folder 3-4)
  - Keep Your Distance, 2002 (Box 11, Folder 5-6)
  - Kingpins, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - The Lady in Question, circa 1970's (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - The Light on Synanon, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Los Angeles County Sherrif's Department, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Malcom in the Middle, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Man from Atlantis, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Med Students, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Miami Vice, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 2-3)
  - The Million Dollar Rip-Off, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Mission Impossible II, 1999 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Mr. Merlin, 1981-1982 (Box 12, Folder 5-6)
  - Muppetvision 3-D, 1989-1990 (Box 12, Folder 7, Box 13, Folder 2)
  - The Naked Truth, 1995-1996 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Network, March 21, 1996 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - New Jack City, November 1990 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Nice Guys Sleep Alone, 1999 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Night Drive, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - North and South II, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 9, Box 13, Folder 6-9)
  - The Nutt House, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 2, Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Oliver Beene, 2002 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - The Owl, 1990-1991 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Pale Blue Ribbon, 1997 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Paramount Studios, 1977-1987 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Perfect Red, 2005 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - The PJs, July 23, 1999 (Box 15, Folder 4-5)
  - Polly, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Reasonable Doubts, 1991-1993 (Box 14, Folder 6-7, Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Rocketeer, 1990 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Roswell, 2001 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Run Joe Run, 1975 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Safari Kid's Club, 2005 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Seinfeld, 1990 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Seven Brides for Seven Brothers, 1982 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Shades of Ray, 2006 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Silk Stalkings, 1994-1995 (Box 17, Folder 5-9)
  - The Single Guy, 1996-1997 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - SKC, 2005 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Snowdrop, 1997 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Sopranos, 2001 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Spencer's Pilots, 1976 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Spider-Man, 2000 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Spy Girl, December 22, 2000 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Staff and crew lists, 1990-2007 (Box 24, Folder 1-4)
  - State of Grace, 2001-2002 (Box 16, Folder 6-7, Box 18, Folder 2-4)
  - Stir Crazy, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - The Strange Possession of Mrs. Oliver, 1976 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Suddenly Susan, 1996 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Superfire, 2001 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Switched at Birth, 1990-1991 (Box 19, Folder 1, Box 18, Folder 7)
  - T.J. Hooker, 1982-1985 (Box 19, Folder 2-4)
  - This Side Up, 2007 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - A Time For Dancing, 2001 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - To Find My Son, 1980 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - The Toolbox Murders, 2003 (Box 20, Folder 1-6)
  - Trauma Center, 1983 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - The Trouble With Larry, 1993 (Box 19, Folder 9, Box 20, Folder 8)
  - The Twilight Zone, 1986 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Under One Roof, 1994 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Untitled Jonathan Katz Project, April 16, 2001 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Untitled Louisiana Project, 2003 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Untitled Miami Pilot, 1992-1994 (Box 21, Folder 3, Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Untitled Projects, circa 1970's-1980's (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Vanishing Act, 1985-1986 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Vega$, 1979-1982 (Box 22, Folder 3-7, Box 21, Folder 6-7)
    Box 22, Folder 4 contains an adult periodical.
  - Wasabi Tuna, 2003 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Waste Land, 2006 (Box 23, Folder 1-2)
  - Webster, 1988 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - The West Wing, circa 2000's (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - The Whereabouts of Jenny, 1990 (Box 23, Folder 4-5)
  - A Winner Never Quits, 1985 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Wizards and Warriors, 1982 (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Wresting Ernest Hemingway, 1992 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Youth in Revolt, 1996 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Laptop, circa 1997-2001 (Box 37)
    Laptop bag containing Macintosh Powerbook G3, Apple 45W power adapter, dongle, and phone jack cords.
  - Floppy disks, circa 1997-2001 (Box 34)
    9 floppy disks originally housed in the laptop case. 3 unlabelled, 1 labelled "Nick's Data Base helix Express Engine", 5 software floppy disks.
- Series 2: Industry Material, circa 1970s-2000s
  This series contains publications and material relating to the film industry from the 1970's-2000's. Materials in this series include catalogs, safety bulletins, business cards, production forms, directories, guidebooks, and union handbooks. A portion of the series was material collected and organized into binders by Smirnoff. There are a number of directories and handbooks that highlight a range of Los Angeles based industry workers such as lighting technicians, studio grips, sound technicians, and make-up and hair stylists. The series also contains a range of materials from the Directors Guild of America and the Alliance of Motion Picture and Television Producers. Other notable materials include directories for ethnic minorities and women in the film industry, and a job application in which Smirnoff details his job history and responsibilities. This series contains explicit adult material.
  This series has been organized chronologically.
  - Production forms, circa 1970's-2000's (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Film finance binder, circa 1970's-1980's (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Production handbook, 1972 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Film process binder, 1972-2002 (Box 25, Folder 4-7)
  - Motion Picture Craft Service binder union 727, circa 1970's (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Industry magazines, 1978-2001 (Box 25, Folder 8, Box 29, Folder 3)
  - United Stuntwomen's Association binder, circa 1980's (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Industry rolodex, circa 1980's-2000's (Box 33)
    Box contains contact information and notes for directors, producers, unit production managers, and photography directors.
  - Industry publications, 1981-2007 (Box 31, Box 32)
    Boxes contain 46 items including catalogs, safety bulletins, business cards, directories, industry guidebooks, and union handbooks.
  - Industry directories, 1985-2005 (Box 30, Folder 3, Folder 7, Box 29, Folder 2, Box 26)
    Box 26, Folder 2 and Box 29, Folder 2 contain directories for the adult film industry.
  - Crew lists binder, 1986-2002 (Box 26, Folder 3-4)
  - Production binder, 1987-1997 (Box 26, Folder 5-6)
  - Industry binder, 1987-2001 (Box 27, Folder 1-3)
  - Filming locations, circa 1990's (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Directors Guild of America material, 1990-2008 (Box 29, Folder 1, Box 30, Folder 6, Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Film production education, 1990 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Epuipment cost reference binder, 1990-1997 (Box 28, Folder 1-2)
  - Screen Actors Guild material, 1992 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Multi-camera crew lists binder, 1992-1997 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - TV production costs binder, 1992-2001 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Film industry task force, 1994 (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - Industry catalogs, circa 1995-2000's (Box 28, Folder 7, Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Union binder, 1996-2002 (Box 29, Folder 4-6)
  - Elder financial abuse, 1997 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Tracking report, 1997 (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - New Mexico job application, 2000 (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - Los Angeles, 2003 (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - Louisiana office of film and video, 2003 (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Notes, 2003 (Box 30, Folder 10)
  - Union agreement, 2003 (Box 30, Folder 11)
- Series 3: Industry Ephemera, circa 1980's-2000's
  This series is comprised of ephemera relating to Smirnoff's work as a production manager, producer, and assistant director from the 1980's–2000's. Included in the series are film production boards used for scheduling. One board contains scheduling strips from an untitled project from 2003. Other items in the collection include director's chair textiles, a promotional clock from the project Felicity, postcards from Paramount Pictures, and a film scheduling software program with floppy disks containing scheduling tests.
  This series has been organized alphabetically by item.
  - Director's chair textiles, circa 1980's-1990's (Box 34)
  - Felicity clock, circa 1998-2002 (Box 34)
  - Film Production Boards, 2003 (undated) (Box 35, Box 36)
    5 film production boards (2 wooden, 3 cardboard). One containing strips dated 2003. Extra colored strips and breakdown pages.
  - Movie Magic floppy disks, 1997 (Box 34)
    1 floppy disk with Movie Magic Screenwriter demo, 2 with tests labelled "Movie Magic test" and "Letter's test", and 4 unlabelled.
  - Movie Magic scheduling, 1999 (Box 30, Folder 12)
    Contains Movie Magic Scheduling 3.0 CD
  - Paramount Pictures postcards, circa 1980's (Box 34)